when historians and culture and a
cultural analysts look at our
contemporary civilization
they frequently use words to describe
the situation that are prefaced by the
word post
we hear this generation called the
post-modern era
or the
post-christian era
or perhaps even more frequently the post
kantian
era
the reason for that description
is that all theoretical thought since
Emmanuel Kant has to be understood in
light of the groundwork that he achieved
in the 18th century
and I think there's a link between
post-contianism
and
what we call the post-christian era
because Emmanuel Kant more than any
other individual
gave the most devastating critique of
classical theism that's ever been
launched and that created a crisis in
apologetics in the rational defense of
historic Christianity and and the like
now
I've mentioned in the past all the way
back at the beginning of our series of a
tendency for Cycles to take place in the
history of theoretical thought
when tension occurs between two dominant
schools of thought that immediately
after that comes a period of skepticism
and that period of skepticism tends to
Prevail until somebody comes along and
produces a new synthesis that will
reconstruct the ground basis for
theoretical thought we saw that in the
tension that arose between the thinking
of Parmenides and heraclitus which was
then resolved by Plato and then we saw
another tension between Plato and
Aristotle which really didn't get
resolved until the Christian synthesis
of Augustine and so on well now in the
17th and 18th century we saw this
terrific tension between the schools of
rationalism and empiricism ending in the
radical skepticism of David Hume
and what follows out of this in the 18th
century are two really different
movements although they're closely
related one was the
origination of the so-called
Enlightenment which will treat at
another time but mainly we're concerned
today with the impact of Emmanuel Kant
now to simplify things we can say that
the whole history of philosophy prior to
Kant can be divided between two general
schools of thought rationalism on the
one hand
and empiricism on the other
so again I'm painting with a broad brush
here and working a little bit Loosely at
this point but if we were to go through
history and look at these strands of
thought under rationalism we might put
Parmenides
and Plato
and uh
plotinus and Augustine and so on
uh dropping down then to Descartes and
leibniz and Spinoza and Pascal on the
empiricism side we would include such
people as heraclitus
and then Aristotle
and then Aquinas
and bacon and then into lock and so on
so that we could as I said if we're
loose enough
put every major thinker Anselm would go
into the rational side into one or the
other of these two camps
now perhaps the most important
philosophical synthesis ever achieved
was that achieved by Kant when he took
both of these schools borrowed from each
he criticized certain aspects of each
side borrowed the good things from each
side and produced a whole new approach
to knowledge
now we'll go over that in a few moments
but after Kant achieved his synthesis
you might think well then that would be
the end of the history of Western
philosophy but in fact what happened is
out of kant's watershed work
came either directly or indirectly all
the modern schools of philosophy that
compete with one another for acceptance
since Kant from Kant we can trace the
roots for example of idealism
of Marxism
of
logical positivism
an analytical philosophy
or existentialism
or phenomenology
or pragmatism
or relativism
or pluralism
that is to say virtually all of the
movements of the 19th and 20th Century
that have emerged since Kant traced
their origins in their roots to some
aspect some dimension of the work that
he initiated
now let's take a few moments to look at
the basics of his synthesis
if you recall we saw that the
differences between the rationals
rationalists and the empiricists
included the rationalists believed in
the priority
of the ah priori that is of innate ideas
rational Concepts whereas the empiric
system that all knowledge was all
posteriori that is after experience and
there were no innate ideas so that
irreconcilable dispute between
rationalism and empiricism was one of
the key things that Kant addressed but
first his approach
kant's approach to this problem was
called the transcendental method
now
there's some ambiguity in the way in
which the term transcendental is used
here but let me try to simplify it for
you
Kant looked at the problems
that were faced both by the empiricists
and the rationalists
he looked at the the graveyard of
empiricism and the skepticism of David
Hume
and it was Hume skepticism that aroused
Kant to try to come up with a
reconstruction of philosophy
uh Kant was a man who lived in
koenigsburg in Prussia he was a an
obscure professor at the University
there he never traveled more than a
hundred miles from his uh place of birth
and no one ever assumed that he would
make any kind of Splash in the
intellectual world but he said he was
awakened from his dogmatic Slumbers by
the work of David Hume and he rose to
the occasion out of a desire to rescue
science to rescue knowledge itself
and so his most important and most
famous work the critique of pure reason
was published in 1781 right around the
same time that the articles of uh of
government for the United States is New
Republic were being processed and we are
told in our country that the most
significant revolution in the last
couple of 300 years was the American
Revolution
but historians of culture argue that the
most significant revolution in the last
300 years was the kantian revolution
because cons New Philosophy had
far-reaching consequences consequences
that still impact the culture in which
we live today because if you look at the
last 250 years
and see what has happened to the church
see what has happened to the classical
synthesis where in the Middle Ages
theology was the queen of the sciences
and philosophy was regarded as her
handmaiden and there was a certain
intellectual credibility to the truth
claims of Christianity
but since the kantian critique of the
traditional Arguments for the existence
of God for example
philosophy has been liberated from
Theology and the impact of Theology and
the church
has declined dramatically in the last
200 years
but let's again go back to what Kant
meant by his transcendental method he
looked at the problems the problems of
truth and how we attain it and he asked
this simple question
not
is there such a thing as knowledge
but he said this if
knowledge is possible
what would there have to be in order to
make it possible in that sense he's
transcending the problem in that sense
he's cutting the gordian knot and he's
saying okay I don't know whether we can
get knowledge or not get knowledge but
if knowledge is possible
how would we proceed what things would
be necessary in order to achieve it
and he said well Locke was right and the
imperious empiricists were right that
all of our knowledge of the external
world
begins with experience
so if science is going to be possible we
are dependent for better for worse upon
sense experience as our starting point
for knowledge and so the beginning
of knowledge is Sensations
now he
disagreed with Descartes and the history
of rationalists who believe that we are
born with certain innate ideas like
Plato argued that we have these ideas
with which we're born and all we have to
do is stimulate the memory to recall or
to recollect those Eternal ideas for
caught there are no innate ideas
but there are
elements that can be called a priori
remember that technically speaking
the term ah priori does not mean before
birth
it means before experience
and so Kant is saying that even though
we don't have any content of knowledge
at Birth
we do have
operi categories that are categories of
the Mind
categories that make it possible for us
to know things before
experiencing them
for example principles like the law of
causality principles like the law of
non-contradiction are not learned from
experience
but nevertheless they are not something
that we're born with in terms of a
content of Concepts but rather they are
rational
categories rational abilities that are
built into the mind so sometimes people
try to diagram kant's approach to
knowledge and speak of his sausage
grinder uh
his sausage grinder epistemology where
there is this funnel at the top where
you put the sausage in and that's the
sensation so you get these Impressions
and these sensual experiences and they
go into the funnel of the sausage
grinder but before anything can come out
of the sausage grinder these Sensations
have to work through the categories of
the Mind
so that the mind is processing these raw
Sensations
and not only that for us to be able to
have
any
meaningful perception of the external
world we always perceive of the external
world
in terms of things or objects
that are in space and time
but do we ever have a sensation or a
direct perception of space
or a direct perception of time I was in
the conversation just the other day
with a young man who was asking me what
time was
and I said I don't know
I said we can Define it in terms of the
some kind of motion of consecutive
moments or consequential moments or
sequential moments
and I said but I can't conceive of time
except
by the relationship of motion to
something physical
how do we tell time
we have clocks a physical object and we
have numbers on the face of the clock
and then we have these different hands
moving like the second hand and I I
often have people stand in front of a
clock and I'll say it's now 12 o'clock
noon and you see the second hand up at
the 12 and I said look down now at the
six
and and the second hand is moving
towards that uh the second hand here's
the 12 and here's the six and here's the
second hand and it is moving in this
direction and I'll say look at the six
and you're looking at the future
but it hasn't arrived yet sort of like
what goes on in the in the countdown of
Times Square and New York New Year's Eve
when people give the final 10 second
countdown
the six here remains future and this
hand sweeps down across the dial and and
you'll have this sense of anticipation
as we get closer and closer and closer
to that future moment that is the six
and then as it comes down here
it goes right past it and I said there
it goes it's gone that which a moment
ago was future
is now passed and we talk about living
in the present but the presence seems to
be hanging hanging there suspended
between the past and the future because
we can't freeze it it won't stand still
it keeps moving
and so how other ways do we measure time
you have water clocks
sundials
sand clocks where the sand is sifting
through this hourglass
every way that we have to tell time in
our normal experience is by
watching some kind of movement
between at least two objects so for us
to have a sense of time we have to have
matter and we have to have motion
and that always raises the philosophical
question what time was it the day before
creation
remember Augustine was asked the
question what was God doing before he
created the universe and his reply was
he was creating hell for Curious Souls
but I mean people like to speculate
about the timelessness of God and the
timelessness Before Time was their time
before there was a world and motion it's
an interesting question again we don't
perceive it nor do we perceive space
purely
because to have a perception of pure
space would be to perceive nothing
and nothing is imperceptible
and this was part of the question that
Hume was struggling with if you recall
when he was asking the question how can
I have a distinct impression of a
distinct sensation why when I'm standing
before of an audience
don't I just experience
undifferentiated blob of Sensations
bombarding my eyes and my ears how is it
that I can distinguish the difference
between
music and Noise
there has to be some kind of
discrimination
some ability to sort things out and to
perceive these Sensations in an orderly
way
now is that because there really is
order out there
and I'm perceiving an orderly universe
or is it all chaos all cacophony
but as I experience this chaos and all
this noise the noise of the sensation
comes into the categories of my brain
am I creating order out of this order as
a human being
well how is it that I can have a
discrete sensation of something in space
and time when I have no direct sensation
of space and time
well Khan said well
you have to have space and time in order
to be able to have a perception and so
he spoke of space and time as what he
called Pure intuitions
that is so now we have
the rational categories the empirical
Sensations and intuition working in this
epistemology
and once we get all through this meat
grinder what comes out the end is
knowledge
so
do we know
that this knowledge
absolutely corresponds to reality no we
don't
now Kant says instead of defining truth
is that which corresponds to reality
Kant declared that truth is a judgment
and he distinguished among different
types of judgments different kinds of
judgments
judgments that are all priori
that is before experience
and judgments that are all posteriori
that comes with or through experience
and then he distinguished between two
other kinds of judgments what he called
analytical judgments
and synthetic judgments
now you recall
that we've used this language before an
analytical statement is a statement that
is true under analysis it is true by
definition an analytical statement would
be
a bachelor is an unmarried man
there's nothing in the predicate
that isn't already in the subject
so that you know the predicate without
ever having to experience it
it's it's true by definition so in that
case an analytical judgment could be a
priori
that is without ever experiencing a
particular man to see if he's married or
not if you say that the man is a
bachelor you already know that he's not
married because the term Bachelor means
unmarried
well working through these synthetic
statements are those statements where we
learn new information The Bachelor is
Rich riches don't necessarily
coincide with bachelor-ness and so you
can find a bachelor that's poor you can
find one that's rich but you can't know
whether the bachelor is Rich or poor
without having an experience of that
Bachelor so far so good
but he said that there are synthetic
statements that are
a posteriori
but also synthetic statements that are
Opera and that created a firestorm of
controversy among later philosophers
because they were arguing
than any concrete information
must depend upon experience but can't
for example argued that the knowledge
that the shortest distance between two
points is a straight line
he said we know that before we're
experiencing it
and yet the concept straight line
does not have within it
the idea of shortness of distance it
only is a quality of Direction
and so the debate goes on but in any
case all of this is working together to
reconstruct philosophy to borrow
necessary ingredients from empiricism
necessary ingredients from rationalism
put them together
in a synthesis
that now makes it possible to proceed
but the proceeding of knowledge is
limited
only to that Arena
where we have access by Sensations
and herein is the crisis in metaphysics
and in theology which we'll look at in
our next lecture